[Music]
oh well you have heard somebody said first there was a word and the Word was God well
what is a word if I speak a language that you do not understand and I utter a word what is
a word for you it's just a sound so ENT it's a sound sound is a reation which is the basis of
everything that there is now how to craft sounds or how to use sounds in a way it's beneficial for
us now before we step into shambavi we should look at this science we will explore this in
a very simple way as to how to use sounds to bring balance and well-being we are also
beginning to learn how to do one small part of shambavi Maham mutra if you have to utter any
kind of sound without using the tongue what are the sounds that you could utter I want you to
experiment and see without using the tongue just try to make sounds uh yes for sure you can do
[Music] a
[Laughter] [Music]
possible anything else h m yes p possible what
else no you can't do that without your
tongue suppose you did not have a tongue what are the sounds you
canot tell you can do a you can do ooh you can do M try any other sound
anything
else
huh someone who is unable to speak a mute person who is unable to speak what are the sounds that he
makes because these three sounds do not need the use of your
tongue so in speech you're using your tongue what is the tongue actually doing what is its
function H yes but what is it doing actually I'm
sorry all right but what is it doing
actually for sure it's [Laughter] wagging so if you remove your tongue you are able
to make only three sounds a o H you're using the tongue placing the tongue in different
positions in your pallette to mix these three sounds and produce all the other sounds that
you produce if you know something about the color television you would know there are only
three basic colors using these three colors you see every other possible color on the
tube similarly there are only three basic sounds using these three sounds you able to produce all
these other sounds the tongue is just helping you to mix these three sounds in many complex
ways now these three sounds ah Wu and Ma are referred
to as the basic sounds or the universal sound
because these three sounds are the basis of all the other sounds that you can
utter if you UT these three sounds together what you
get it's not
oh if you open your mouth and expel the hair it becomes ah as you're closing it
halfway down it becomes U when you close it it becomes M almost every creature can
utter these three sounds if you have a dog or a cat at home if he yawns what does he do
[Laughter] um if you opens his mouth it does a halfway down it does U closing m
so these are the three basic sounds which are the very basis of all the
other sounds that you cannot tell why are they referred to as the universal
sounds today modern science is telling you the whole existence is just a reation of
energy it is the same energy vibrating in different ways which makes it so so many
things if the whole existence is a vibration where
there's a vibration there is bound to be a sound isn't it
so where there's a vibration there is bound to be
a sound so the whole existence is a complex amalgamation of
sounds this is one kind of sound that is another kind of sound every form
is a certain kind of sound if you feed any sound into an oscilloscope the sound
measuring instrument depending upon its frequency amplitude and other dimensions
of the sound it gives out a certain form that means every sound has a form attached to it
similarly every form has a sound attached to it so this relationship between the sound and the
form is known as the signs of
mantras now modern science is proving to you the whole existence is just a vibration where
there's a vibration there is bound to be a sound so the whole existence is sound and the
root sound for all this complex amalgamation of sounds is Sound a Vu and Ma or um so um is
known as the universal sound or the basic sound in the creation if this is true how come only
a certain religion seems to be using it as a brand for themselves and nowhere else it
is known that is not true wherever there is a real being there sound arm will be
there for example Christianity born in
Jerusalem where the language at that time was
AR aric language has a certain infliction where sound is
dominant so this this influence of the language and culture enters everything that you do whatever
you're doing in your life whatever you're expressing in your life the influence of
your culture and your language enters into it that is the significance of the East that is
the significance of these Traditions that we took elaborate care to see that our cultural
and language aspects do not enter the spiritual process elaborate elaborate care was taken to
see that language and culture does not enter spiritual process because language and culture
keeps changing by the generation from time to time your cultural and language aspects keep
changing but we do not want those influences to distort the spiritual process so great care
was taken about this for this we established a certain system which we call as the guru shisha
parara that means a master disciple traditions where if someone experiences something within
himself he will look for a person who will hold this truth about his life not as a part
of his life not as his profession not as his career not as his hobby but about his life
only to such a person it is given now now he carries it through his life without a single
Distortion and offers it to the next generation and the Next Generation and the Next Generation
so this these Master disciple Traditions or Guru shisha parara grew and flourished for thousands
of years so as a rule anything that is spiritual was never written down so this transmission of
knowledge this transmission of spiritual knowing was transmitted by sound Never by writing down
only verbally only orally these oral Traditions grew and this kept the Purity in the east no
other culture on the planet could afford this because most cultures are were constantly in
situations of strife and War all the time when it comes to human consciousness when it comes
to understanding the mechanics of life process nowhere else has it been explored with as much
profoundness and as much variety as it's been done here simply because of an established culture for
thousands of years undisturbed not ravaged by
Wars not ravaged by other kinds of influences
a stable culture which grew for a long long period of time evolved this and spread this culture where
this master disciple Traditions carried on so sound um was carried from generation to
generation but the same things happen in other cultures and they got distorted influenced by
language and culture so in Christianity whatever they close with today whatever
they say they close it with amen if you look at it the way it is said at the Vatican it's always
[Music] saiden you take off the n and say
[Music] Amen oh if you want to understand this you
can see a similar infliction in Tamil the Tamil speaking
people see now for example Ram you know Ram born in [Laughter]
ayodya Ram had series of misfortunes in his life he came down south when
he came South when Ram entered Andra
Pradesh and Karnataka people called him
Rama then he crossed the tamilnad border people called him
Raman if Krishna comes to Tamil NAD what will you do ra Krishna if Arjun comes to Tamil Nadu what
do you do arjunan if beam comes to tamut what do you do bean whoever enters tamut B they get
unified this infliction of in
Tamil is much stronger than her
mik take out the N it's just arm today this amen has gone to United States of America and become a
man this is cultural and language distortions which happen Islam born also in the same region
under the same cultural and language influences they are saying aan take away an and and say a
mean um oh it's the same sound because wherever a human being becomes silent by his own nature
not school teacher silence not plugging your ear silence if you become silent by
your own nature sound um will reverberate in the system because the root sound for
your physical existence is sound am when am reverberates it starts from just beneath the
navl and ends at the tip of your nose this reverberation will just happen by itself so
wherever a human being truly sat quietly utter quietness within himself he always became aware
of the sound um when he transmitted it it got distorted over a period of time according to
to Language and Cultural influences even in India has become om it is not oh you
open your mouth and say ah gently close your mouth it becomes o you close it it becomes
M [Music]
uh
[Music] sound H um has innumerable benefits even today if anybody come here with any kind
of P psychological disturbances the first prescription is always um you do this for
a few weeks you settle down and then we go into other aspects I can show you hundreds of people
for whom medically it was believed that they have to be in psychiatric medication for the
rest of their life have completely walked out of the need for medication simply by uttering arm if
you are suffering from excessive fear distorted dreams bad dreams nightmares unstable mind
unstable body if your general Constitution is weak you tend to fall sick too often
particularly children if they have attention disorders daily atance of am for a few minutes
a day will make a enormous difference for you if you have problems that you
are unable to do anything with a certain resolve in your life daily utterance of
am will be truly trans transformational for you within a couple of weeks you can
notice a phenomenal difference in the way you function because this is the basic sound in
your physical existence when you utter this arm it's very important that you're aware of
the nature of the vibrations that it causes any repetition without the necessary awareness will
bring dullness into you repetitiveness will make you dull like if you sit here and say r
r you will become dull unfortunately most people understand this dullness as
peace if you are dull you will be peaceful
if you are
dead totally peaceful isn't it you becoming dull and peaceful is of no consequence if you can be
exuberantly alive and be peaceful it's worthwhile you become like this and you're peaceful it is no
good repetitiveness will do this to your mind so when you UT to the sound um the sound begins just
beneath the navl and ends at the tip of your nose so every utterance you must move with awareness
with the retion you must move your awareness along with the vibration only then this awareness builds
up into your phenomenal Force within you but without the awareness if you just sit
here you'll become dull right now we will just do this sit
or cross leg posture you take your left heel and push it into your perum perum means between the
anal outlet and the genital there is a little space which is known as a perum in the yogic
terminology this is known as the muladhara so you push your heel into that right leg you just place
it comfortably in front of you whichever way it's comfortable for you so this is called Earth the
SAS here we will do one mudra use the four finger and the thumb to touch at the very tips and form
a circle between them but these four fingers should remain together there should be no Gap
here do not allow a gap cap here the four fingers are together the forefinger and the thumb form a
circle and hold it facing upward when you hold the mudra you must place it in that place where
your arms will be loose you find that point on your thigh where your arms will be very
loose only the mudra should be tight from the tip of your finger to your wrist there must
be little tension but that tension should not extend into your forearm or your bicep muscle
only the mudra should be tight without employing your forarm if you employ your forarm the mudra
will turn negative so you're sitting in theas holding the mud this is the posture we will be
using close your eyes we will UT this sound repeat after me okay don't go with
me [Music] uh
yes [Music]
ah [Music]
uh [Music]
are you able to notice the reverberation moving from the navl to the tip of your
nose is it noticeable you must be aware of this when you utter this so uttering
sound AR has innumerable benefits any kind of stabilization that is necessary for the
physiology or the psychological situation can be very easily achieved by uttering sound AR
now this whole science of name form relationship or sound and form relationship is perceived in a
certain state of perception which is known as
RAR prna RAR means if you look at a certain
aspect of nature now your perception is such the sound associated with that you are aware
of now what you do is you give that sound as the name to that form so when you utter the
sound on where you utter the name the sound and the form that you're referring to are connected
if you have Mastery over the sound that you utter you also begin to have Mastery over the form this
is the science of mantras if one moves into a certain state of perception which is known
asna every form that you see you can figure out the sound attached to it
and simply by uttering the sound you connect with the form you can
experience the form just by uttering the sound if you know something about quantum
mechanics you would know that in quantum mechanics there are
three fundamental aspects these three aspects are referred to as forces of
creation forces of Maintenance forces of Destruction according to Quantum
Mechanics there are only three things in the existence creative
action maintenance action destructive action is that so is that so this is
science today the modern scientists refer to these three fundamental forces either as a b c
or XYZ or whatever they like the same three forces here in in India we call them Brahma Vishnu and
Mahesh Brahma is the creative operator Vishnu is the maintenance operator Shiva is the
Destroyer this is a dialectical culture so science was taught in a story form some
of the things that they have very commonly said across cultural divides is if education
happens in story form then suppressive nature of information can be taken away this is what
they did this is quantum mechanics for you a few thousand years ago Brahma is the creative
operator Vishnu maintenance Shiva the Destroyer if you want to destroy something what do you need
let's say we want to destroy the city in which you live what do you need you are enough or we
need something [Laughter] more uh what do we need a bomb isn't it a bomb means what if you put too
much energy at one point explosion will happen so if you want to destroy you need energy Shiva
is the Destroyer who is his concert [Music] shaki Shakti means energy to destroy you need
energy well he's got her sitting by his side now
Shiva is personified as masculine the energy is
personified as feminine so this is the destructive force if you want to create something what do you
need you need intelligence and knowledge isn't it Brahma is the creative operator
who is his coner [Music] sarasti she is the goddess of intelligence and knowledge
to create that's what you need so that's what you have the third pair became too
popular wishnu and
Lakshmi Vishnu is the maintenance operator
Lakshmi is the goddess of money and wealth why
maintenance and money are clued together what if you want to maintain you need
money yes that is also
true if you want to maintain you need money but the important thing is if you want to make
money you should know how to maintain you do fanciful things you don't make money see who
are the richest people which class of people are the richest people in any given Society
always the businessman isn't it what does a businessman do from morning to evening create
destroy or maintain maintaining every day day in and day out he sits in his shop it doesn't
take any dazzling Brilliance to do this but it takes perseverance every day every day
every day sitting there and maintaining and maintaining and maintaining now money happens
you may be brilliant but if your activity is intermittent you don't make much money
isn't it so if you want to make money you must have the perseverance to maintain otherwise you
don't make money so Vishnu and Lakshmi together now these three forces we say
here without the the concurrence of Brahma
Vishnu and Mahesh you cannot even move a
blade of grass this does not mean three people in Partnership are moving Blades of grasses what
this means is every atom is constructed with proton neutron electron this is Brahma Vishnu
and Mahesh without the concurrence of these three forces you definitely cannot even move
a blade of grass isn't it so this is quantum mechanics for you I won't go into the whole
story we can propound the whole quantum mechanics through this story this is how
it was done long time ago now these forces have also taken certain positions in your
body Naval is vishnu's position this is the maintenance
center in yoga this is known as the manipuraka chakra in the forestation cultures this is
known as Hara so this manipura chakra is the only point in your body where all the 72,000
channels of Prana there are 72,000 IES or channels or Pathways in this body all of them are meeting
at this one point and redistributing themselves this is the only Point your manipura car Yara
is located about 34 of an inch below your naal and that is the point where all the nadis meet
and redistribute themselves and the mantra for this chakra is sound ah if you you say ah you
will see the reverberation will start just 34 of an inch below your navl just try this and see
ah is that so this is the only sound which takes the reverberation right across the body because
this is the only point in the body where all the
72,000 nadis meet and redistribute themselves this
is your maintenance center even when you were in your mother's o where was the maintenance pipe
connected to you at the naval now the maintenance pipe is severed but still the maintenance center
is here so sound a is Vishnu sound this is the maintenance sound if you UT sound ah reverberation
will start just beneath the the navl and spread across the body no other sound can do this if you
UT sound ooh you will see it begins just where the rib cage meets just beneath that there's a soft
spot in yoga we call this anahata anahata means the unstruck sound so sound o begins from here and
the riv brations will flow this way and then move upward it'll never go this way just see this o
[Music] is that so this is brahma's sound this is a creative Center and
this is brahma's sound if you utter the sound
M you will see the rioration will start from
the pit of your throat and generally spread to the upper regions of your
[Music]
body is that so so this is shiva's sound this is at vishi vishi literally means a
filter if your vishi is active you can filter everything that comes to you taking only what's
needed you know Shiva is referred to as nilak or vishak because he drinks poison and he stops it
right here he doesn't let it affect his system poison need not necessarily mean that you have
to consume it in the form of food or drink a thought can poison your life an emotion can
poison your life an idea can poison your life yes a wrong idea a wrong thought a wrong emotion can
completely mess your life up so if your wishi is active you filter it down here if it's right
here you can always spit it out that's why when you don't like somebody people want to
spit they want the worst to go to
them it is very beautifully expressed like this if you have Mastery over sound ah you can become
extraordinarily Rich if you have Mastery over sound ooh you you can become extraordinarily
intelligent if you have Mastery over sound
M you can become extraordinarily powerful
but when you utter sound um you have to ensure that a Vu and Ma are approximately
equal because if you have any one of them in excess you will become messed up you have too
much money neither the intelligence nor the power to employ this money you will be in lot
of trouble You' seen people without money they would be better off with money they completely
ruined too much intelligence neither the money nor the power to employ this again
trouble have you seen a lot of people very intelligent people complete mess too much
power neither the intelligence nor the money lot of trouble these three things must be in Balance
within your only then you live a balanced life but now you want money so you don't
[Laughter] say you ensure a Vu and
Ma are approximately equal if you
want to do individual sad in just a or just who or just um it has to be
done under expert guidance but um is a basic sound everybody is free to utter
[Music] this [Music] [Applause] [Music]
just do this sit the or cross- leg
posture use the four finger and the thumb to touch the very tips and form a circle between them but
these four fingers should remain together there should be no Gap here do not allow a gap here
the four fingers are together the four finger and the thumb form a circle and hold it facing
upward when you hold the mudra you must place it in that place where your arms will be loose
you find that point on your thigh where your arms will be very loose only the mudra should be tight
from the tip of your finger to your wrist there must be little tension but that tension should
not extend into your forearm or your Bice BP muscle only the mudra should be tight without
employing your forearm if you employ your forearm the mudra will turn negative so you're sitting in
sidas holding the mudra so when you UT to the sound AR you open your mouth and say ah gently
close your mouth it becomes o you close it it becomes M the sound begins just beneath the
navl and ends at the tip of your nose so every utterance you must move with awareness with the
reverberation you must move your awareness along with the vibration only then this awareness builds
up into your phenomenal Force within you keep your spine erect close your eyes we will UT this
[Music] [Laughter] [Music]
sound
M [Laughter] [Music]
ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter] [Music] ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] a
ah [Music] [Laughter] [Music] a [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter]
ah [Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter] [Music]
a
[Laughter] [Music] m [Laughter]
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] M [Laughter] [Music]
ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter] [Music] ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] ah [Music] [Laughter] [Music]
uh [Music] ah [Laughter] [Music] ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter]
ah [Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter]
a
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter] [Music]
m
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] M [Laughter]
ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter] a
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] ah
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] a uh
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] oh [Music] [Laughter]
a
[Music] [Laughter] [Music] [Laughter]
[Music] [Laughter] [Music]
m
please open your
eyes
that